Guide to the Edward C. Tabler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward C. Tabler papers
1863-1977
1940-1977
MS 1317
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
The papers consist of correspondence, research notes, bibliographies and photographs, principally relating to Edward Tabler's interest in the early history of South Africa and Rhodesia. Over half the letters to Tabler relate to his research and his correspondents include not only other scholars, but also the descendants of early explorers and settlers. These letters contain considerable substantive information, several illustrated with hand-drawn maps of southern Africa. Others discuss the political changes in Rhodesia (circa 1950-1970) from the point of view of the white minority. His research material includes typed transcriptions of nineteenth century South African diaries and manuscripts, his own notebooks and photographs, a bibliography of his writings, and biographical information.
Tabler, Edward C.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence, notebooks, bibliographies, and photographs are available on microfilm (3,025 frames on 3 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM153.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Edward C. Tabler estate, 1979.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of Edward C. Tabler, Africanist and author. Over half of the collection consists of letters to Tabler from Africa, England, and the United States devoted primarily to research and publication of his writings on the early history of South Africa and Rhodesia. In connection with these writings he corresponded not only with other scholars but with descendants of early explorers and settlers in order to trace family correspondence, diaries, and accounts of southern Africa, a number of which he subsequently edited for publication. Enclosed in several letters are hand-drawn maps of Southern Africa (folders 17, 27, 63), while one letter from George L. Harrison (1940 Jan 2: folder 33a) encloses correspondence and receipts from 1842 to 1919.
Also reflected in the correspondence is Tabler's interest in collecting Africana and antiquarian books, and in big game hunting. One other recurrent topic is contemporary politics in Rhodesia and South Africa, especially the changes in the Rhodesian government from the 1950s through the 1970s, discussed from the point of view of the white citizenry.
The remainder of the collection is made up primarily of looseleaf notebooks of research notes and bibliographies compiled by Tabler, as well as typed transcripts of diaries and other manuscripts from nineteenth century southern Africa. There are also a biographical sketch and clippings about Tabler, a bibliography of his writings and reviews of them, several photographs, and other miscellaneous items.
Biographical / Historical
Edward C. Tabler (1916-1977) was an engineer who received his B.S. degree from the University of West Virginia in 1938, and his M.S. degree in 1940. He held various positions with Union Carbide, and was the author of many books on the history of South Africa and big game hunting.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 153 instead of the originals.
Africa, Southern -- History; Africa; South Africa -- History; Zimbabwe -- History; Diaries; Historians; Schapera, I. (Isaac), 1905-2003; Tabler, Edward C.; Wright, Howell, 1882-1954
- Inventory, 1863-1977
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1945, 1948, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Alexander, Otto J., 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - Allen, John, and Patricia, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - Anderson, J. B. W., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Anderson, Jeremy L., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Arkwright, C. H., 1967-1968, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Axelson, Eric, 1959-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - B, 1940, 1945-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - Balkema, A. A., 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - Barber, Rex, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - Barclay, Edgar N., 1939 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Beadle, Hugh, 1963-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Bell, Enoch, 1940 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Bell, William, 1933 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Betts, Robert B., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Botha, J. S. Frikkie, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - C, 1945-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Campbell, Killie, 1945-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
    - Chadwick, W. S., 1934 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 15, Reel 1U)
    - Chapman, W. J. B., 1963-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Clark, J. Desmond, and Betty, 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17, Reel 1U)
    - Clay, Gervas, 1961-1963, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - Collins, M. O., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
    - Coupland, R., 1942 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
    - Cripwell, H. A., 1957, 1961, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - D, 1953-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - DeKoch, W. J., 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22, Reel 1U)
    - E, 1943-1947, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 1U)
    - F, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 1U)
    - Fairlie, J. O., 1958 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 25, Reel 1U)
    - Forwood, C., 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26, Reel 1U)
    - Fosbrooke, Henry A., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 27, Reel 1U)
    - Frewin, Hugh, Otto, and Roger, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 28, Reel 1U)
    - G, 1946-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29, Reel 1U)
    - Gibson, Janet, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30, Reel 1U)
    - Glyn, Richard, 1960, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30, Reel 1U)
    - Gordon, Joan, 1959-1960, 1969, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31, Reel 1U)
    - Gunn, Mary D., 1945-1946, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 31, Reel 1U)
    - Guy, G. L., 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31, Reel 1U)
    - H, 1939, 1948, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32, Reel 1U)
    - Harrison, George L., 1940-1955 (Box 1, Folder 33, Reel 1U)
    - Hayes, Stephen T. W., 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 34, Reel 1U)
    - Hogarth, T. J., 1945, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34, Reel 1U)
    - Holt, David N., 1961-1962, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34, Reel 1U)
    - I, 1960 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 35, Reel 1U)
    - J, 1946, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 36, Reel 1U)
    - Jeffreys, Harry W., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37, Reel 1U)
    - Jeffreys, M. K., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 37, Reel 1U)
    - K, 1945-1971 (Box 1, Folder 38, Reel 1U)
    - Kennedy, R. F. ( Africana Notes and News ), 1944-1959 (Box 1, Folder 39, Reel 1U)
    - Keynes, Geoffrey, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 40, Reel 1U)
    - Keynes, Quentin, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 40, Reel 1U)
    - King, D. W., 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 40, Reel 1U)
    - L, 1965, 1973, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 41, Reel 2U)
    - Langham-Carter, R. R., 1972, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 42, Reel 2U)
    - Leaske, L. M., 1949 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 43, Reel 2U)
    - Long, Una, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 43, Reel 2U)
    - Lyell, Denis D., 1931-1933, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 43, Reel 2U)
    - M, 1939-1940, 1950-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 44, Reel 2U)
    - Middleton, Dorothy, 1962-1977 (Box 2, Folder 45, Reel 2U)
    - Morgan, V., 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 46, Reel 2U)
    - Morris, Donald, 1966-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 46, Reel 2U)
    - Murray, John, 1939, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 46, Reel 2U)
    - N, 1946, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Newill, Alan S., 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - O, 1947-1961 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Orford, Julian G., 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - P, 1961, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 51, Reel 2U)
    - Parry, Constance, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Pease, A., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Pulham, G. Joan, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - R, 1940-1976 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Rasmussen, Kent, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Reitz, O. G., 1965 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Ribbink, Paul, 1940 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Roosevelt, K., 1933 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 56, Reel 2U)
    - Rosenfels, Boet, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - Rosenfels, Lois, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - S, 1940, 1945-1975 (Box 2, Folder 58, Reel 2U)
    - Samson, Richard, 1956-1972 (Box 2, Folder 59, Reel 2U)
    - Schapera, I., 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 60, Reel 2U)
    - Smith, Anna, 1950-1954, 1959-1962, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 61, Reel 2U)
    - Smith, K., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 61, Reel 2U)
    - Stone, John T., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 61, Reel 2U)
    - Strutt, Daphne, 1957-1968 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Summers, Roger, 1954-1971 (Box 2, Folder 63, Reel 2U)
    - T, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Tairton, M., 1958 July 3 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Talbot, Dorothy, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Tanner, P. G., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 66, Reel 2U)
    - Tapson, Ross, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 66, Reel 2U)
    - Tredgold, Barbara, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 67, Reel 2U)
    - Tredgold, Margaret, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 67, Reel 2U)
    - Tredgold, R. C., 1946-1972 (Box 2, Folder 68, Reel 2U)
    - U-V, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 69, Reel 2U)
    - Van der Riet, F. G., 1959, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 70, Reel 2U)
    - Varley, D. H., 1944-1961 (Box 2, Folder 70, Reel 2U)
    - W, 1938-1976 (Box 2, Folder 71, Reel 2U)
    - Wallis, J. P. R., 1941-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 72, Reel 2U)
    - Williams, Bill, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Wright, Howell, 1944-1949 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Wright, Peter, 1967, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - X, Y, Z, 1943, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
  - Notebooks
    - "Ethnology, Tribal History, Geography, Missionaries' Road, Historic Baobabs", Undated (Box 3, Folder 76, Reel 3U)
    - "List of Articles from The Field ", 1867-1891 (Box 3, Folder 77, Reel 3U)
    - "Pioneers of Southern Africa", Undated (Box 3, Folder 78, Reel 3U)
    - Typescript of diaries of Guy Dawnay, 1872-1874 (Box 3, Folder 79, Reel 3U)
    - Typescripts of South African diaries, 1863-1880 (Box 3, Folder 80, Reel 3U)
    - Typescripts of South African manuscripts, 1863, 1867-1871 (Box 4, Folder 81, Reel 4)
    - "South African Bibliography", 1939-1956 (Box 4, Folder 82, Reel 4)
  - Biographical information and newspaper clippings about E. C. Tabler, 1967, 1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 83, Reel 4)
  - "A Bibliography of the Writings of Edward C. Tabler", 1976 June (Box 4, Folder 84, Reel 4)
  - Reviews and book notices of writings by Tabler, 1956-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 84, Reel 4)
  - Photographs, 1965, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 85, Reel 4)
  - Lists of correspondence and miscellaneous papers, Undated (Box 4, Folder 86, Reel 4)